<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<chapter xml:id="chapter_6" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Logic: Propositions and Truth Tables</title>
<idx>Propositions and Truth Tables</idx>
<section xml:id="reading-6"><title>Reading Assignment</title>
<p>Read sections 3.1 and 3.2 of Applied Discrete Structures.  In Logic, we focus on the truth values of propositions, which are declarative sentences that are either true or false.  Later we will consider propositions that involve variables that determine the truth of a proposition. But for now, we focus on how propositions can be combined to create new propositions, much as we combine numbers to get other numbers.</p>
<question><title>Response Question</title><statement><p>  Suppose you were given a proposition generated by 100 propositional variables and you are asked whether there is at least one assignment of truth values that you could assign to these variables to make the proposition true. Why is constructing a truth table not practical.  If you decided to examine all possible assignments of truth values and your computer could check one million cases per second, approximately how long would it take to check all cases? </p></statement></question>
<p>Also, turn in solutions to these exercises: </p>
<exercises><exercisegroup>
	<exercise><statement><p>
For each of the following propositions, identify simple propositions, express the compound proposition in symbolic form, and determine whether it is true or false:</p>
<p><ol marker="(a)">
<li><p>The world is flat or zero is an even integer.</p></li>
<li><p>If 432,802 is a multiple of 4, then 432,802 is even.</p></li>
<li><p>5 is a prime number and 6 is not divisible by 4. </p></li>
<li><p><m>3 \in \mathbb{Z}</m> and <m>3 \in  \mathbb{Q}</m>.</p></li>
<li><p><m>2/3 \in  \mathbb{Z}</m> and <m>2/3 \in  \mathbb{Q}</m>.</p></li>
<li><p>The sum of two even integers is even and the sum of two odd integers is odd.</p></li>
</ol></p></statement></exercise>
		<exercise><statement><p>Construct the truth tables of:
<ol marker="(a)" cols="2">
<li><p>  <m>\neg (p\land  q )</m></p></li>
<li><p> <m>(p \land q)\land r</m> </p></li>
</ol></p></statement></exercise>
		</exercisegroup></exercises>
</section>
<section xml:id="questions-6"><title>In-Class Exercises</title>
<p></p>
<exercises><exercisegroup>
  <exercise><statement><p>Reword the following statements into <q>If...then</q> statements.
		<ol marker="(a)">
		<li><p>No resident of Chelmsford likes hot peppers.</p></li>
		<li><p>For 3+7=10, it is necessary that cows fly.</p></li>
		<li><p>For 3+7=10, it is sufficient that cows fly.</p></li>
		<li><p>Lowell is the oldest city in Massachusetts unless mermaids exist.</p></li>
		<li><p>I carry an umbrella when it rains.</p></li>
		</ol>  
  </p></statement></exercise>
  <exercise><statement> <p>Construct the truth table for <m>(p \lor q) \land (p\lor \neg q)</m>.   Notice anything about the result?</p></statement></exercise>
   <exercise><statement><p>
Consider the statement “If Boris visits Hampton Beach, then he eats fried clams.”
			<ol marker="(a)">
				<li> <p>Write the converse of the statement.</p></li>
				<li> <p>Write the contrapositive of the statement.</p></li>
				<li> <p>Is it possible for the contrapositive to be false? If it was, what would that tell you?</p></li>
				<li> <p>Suppose the original statement is true, and that Boris eats fried clams. Can you conclude anything (about his travels)?</p></li>
				<li> <p>Suppose the original statement is true, and that Boris does not eat fried clams. Can you conclude anything (about his travels)?</p></li>
			</ol>
   </p></statement></exercise>
<exercise><statement> <p>
        Consider the statement,
        <q>If a number is triangular or square, then it is not prime</q>
        <ol marker="(a)">
          <li><p>Make a truth table for the statement <m>(T \vee S) \rightarrow \neg P</m>.</p> </li>
          <li> <p>If you believed the statement was false,
              what properties would a counterexample need to possess?
              Explain by referencing your truth table.</p></li>
          <li> <p>If the statement were true, what could you conclude about the number 5657, which is definitely prime? Again, explain using the truth table.</p> </li>
        </ol>
      </p>
    </statement></exercise>
</exercisegroup></exercises>
</section>
<!-- 
<section xml:id="handouts-6"><title>Handouts</title>
<p>None</p>
</section>
 -->
</chapter>