<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<chapter xml:id="chapter_7" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Equivalence, Implication, and Laws of Logic</title>
<idx>Equivalence</idx>
<idx>Implication</idx>
<idx>Laws of Logic</idx>
<section xml:id="reading-7"><title>Reading Assignment</title>
<p>Read sections 3.3 and 3.4 of Applied Discrete Structures. Two propositions may be totally unrelated.  For example, <q>It snowed today.</q> and <q>I played chess today.</q> are likely to be unrelated.  Yet <q>It snowed today.</q> and <q>I played golf today.</q> are two propositions that are related in that it is unlikely that both are true.  In these two sections we introduce the ideas of equivalence and implication, which give us a precise way to talk about how propositions are related.</p>
<question><title>Response Question</title><statement><p>  Explain why every proposition implies a tautology. </p></statement></question>
<p>Also, turn in solutions to these exercises: </p>
	<exercises><exercisegroup>
<exercise><statement><p><ol marker="(a)">
<li><p>Construct the truth table for <m>x= (p \land  \neg q) \lor  (r \land  p)</m>.</p></li>
<li><p>Find an example other than <m>x</m> itself of a proposition generated by <m>p</m>, <m>q</m>, and <m>r</m> that is equivalent to <m>x</m>.</p></li>
<li><p>Find an example of a proposition that is not equivalent to <m>x</m> or a contradiction  that implies <m>x</m>.</p></li>
<li><p> Find an example of a proposition that is not equivalent to <m>x</m> or a tautology that is implied by <m>x</m>.</p></li>
</ol></p></statement></exercise>
		
<exercise><statement><p>Show that the common fallacy <m>(p\to  q) \land  \neg p \Rightarrow  \neg q</m> is not a law of logic.</p></statement></exercise>
		</exercisegroup></exercises>
</section>
<section xml:id="questions-7"><title>In-Class Exercises</title>
<p></p>
<exercises><exercisegroup>

<exercise><statement><p>Find a proposition that is equivalent to <m>p \lor  q</m> and uses only conjunction and negation. </p></statement></exercise>

<exercise><statement><p><!-- Based on a problem from Oscar Levin's book -->
        Frankie Fib was telling you what he consumed yesterday afternoon.
        He tells you, <q>I had either popcorn or raisins.
        Also, if I had cucumber sandwiches, then I had soda.
        But I didn't drink soda or tea.</q>
        Of course you know that Frankie is the worlds worst liar,
        and everything he says is false.
        What did Frankie have to eat and drink?
      </p></statement></exercise>

<exercise><statement><p>Construct the truth table for <m>(p \rightarrow q) \land (q \rightarrow r) \land (r \rightarrow p)</m>.   Notice anything about the result?</p></statement></exercise>

<exercise><statement><p>The significance of the Sheffer Stroke is that it is a <q>universal</q> operation in that all other logical operations can be built from it.
<ol marker="(a)">
<li><p>Prove that <m>p | q</m> is equivalent to <m>\neg (p \land  q)</m>.</p></li>
<li><p>Prove that <m>\neg p \Leftrightarrow  p | p</m>.</p></li>
<li><p>Build <m>\land</m> using only the Sheffer Stroke.</p></li>
<li><p>Build <m>\lor</m> using only the Sheffer Stroke.</p></li>
</ol></p></statement></exercise></exercisegroup></exercises>

</section>
<section xml:id="handouts-7"><title>The Sheffer Stroke</title>
<idx>Equivalence</idx>
<p>Another logical operation is the Sheffer Stroke, which is the subject of one of the exercises.</p>
<table xml:id="tt-scheffer">
<title>Truth Table for the Sheffer Stroke</title>
<tabular  halign="center">
<row><cell><m>p</m> </cell><cell> <m>q</m> </cell><cell> <m>p \mid q</m> </cell></row>
<row><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell></row>
<row><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 1 </cell></row>
<row><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 0 </cell><cell> 1 </cell></row>
<row><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 1 </cell><cell> 0 </cell></row>
 </tabular>
</table>
</section>
</chapter>	