<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<chapter xml:id="chapter_109" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Properties of Groups </title>
<idx><h>group</h><h>properties</h></idx>
<section xml:id="reading-109"><title>Reading Assignment</title>
<p>Read Section 11.3 of <em>Applied Discrete Structures</em>.  In this section we examine some of the basic theorems that follow immediately from the axioms of a group. Reviewing the proofs is a good exercise in solidifying an understanding of the axioms. In most cases, these theorems are applied in later work without explicitly stating them. </p>
<question><title>Response Question</title><statement><p>SageMath can be used to explore concrete groups.  It can't be used to prove significant theorems, but you can verify that the theorems are true.  Here is one particular group's operation table generated using Sage. The group, with domain <c>[a,b,c,d,e,f,g,h]</c>, is in a family called the dihedral groups, and will be encountered in Section 15.3. For the purposes of this question, notice that in the body of the table, each element appears exactly once in each row and column.  Which theorem guarantees that this is always true for a group's operation table?</p>
	<sage>
			<input>
			G=DihedralGroup(4)
			G.cayley_table()
			</input>
	<output>
	*  a b c d e f g h
	 +----------------
	a| a b c d e f g h
	b| b a d c f e h g
	c| c g a e d h b f
	d| d h b f c g a e
	e| e f g h a b c d
	f| f e h g b a d c
	g| g c e a h d f b
	h| h d f b g c e a
	</output>
	</sage>
</statement>
<answer><p>Any of of the following theorems could be applied to make this observation: Cancellation Laws, Linear Equations in a Groups, or the Pigeonhole Principle.</p></answer></question>
<p>Also, do these exercises:</p>
<exercises><exercisegroup>
	<exercise><statement><p>Suppose <m>[G;*]</m> is a group with <m>a,b,c \in G</m>.   Solve the equation <me>a*x*a^{-1}*b= c</me	> for <m>x</m>.</p></statement><solution><p></p></solution></exercise>
	<exercise><statement><p>Notice that <m>\{1,2,3\} \cap \{1,2\} = \{1,2,3,4\} \cap \{1,2\}</m>, yet <m>\{1,2,3\}  \neq \{1,2,3,4\} </m>. Does this contradict the <xref ref="theorem-11-3-cancellation" text="title"/>? Explain your answer.</p></statement><solution><p>A</p></solution></exercise>
		</exercisegroup></exercises>
</section>
<section xml:id="questions-109"><title>In-Class Exercises</title>
<p></p>
<exercises><exercisegroup>
		<exercise><statement><p>Prove that if <m>a^2 = e</m> for all elements <m>a</m> in a group <m>G</m>, then <m>G</m> must be abelian.</p></statement><hint><p>Given <m>a, b \in G</m>, apply the premise to <m>a*b</m>.</p></hint></exercise>
			<exercise><statement><p>Suppose <m>[G;*]</m> is a group and <m>a \in G</m>.  Define <m>f_a:G \to  G</m> by <m>f_a(x) = a * x</m>.  If we compose two such functions, <m>f_a</m> and <m>f_b</m> where <m>a, b \in G</m>, what function do we get for <m>f_a \circ f_b</m>?</p></statement><solution><p></p></solution></exercise>
	
<exercise>
		<statement>
		<p>This problem anticipates a future topic that you can plausibly discover on your own. Functions like the ones in the previous problem can be of use in this one.</p>
		<p>Suppose <m>[G;*]</m> is a finite group of order <m>n</m>. The <xref ref="theorem-11-3-finite" text="title"/> in Section 10.3 states that if <m>a\in G</m>, there exists a positive integer, <m>m</m> less than <m>n</m> such that <m>a^m=e</m>.  Prove that the least such positive integer is a divisor of <m>n</m>.</p></statement>
		<hint><p>You can partition <m>G</m> into subsets of equal cardinality.</p></hint><solution><p>Let <m>H</m> be the set of distinct powers of <m>a</m>.  This is a finite set since it's a subset of a finite set.  Pick any element <m>a</m> of <m>G</m> that's not in <m>H</m>.  The function <m>f_a:H \rightarrow G</m> from the last problem of the week is a one-to-one function (this implied by the cancellation laws).  The range of <m>f_a</m>,  <m>f_a(H)</m>, has the same cardinality as <m>H</m>.  Keep repeating the process, at each stage selecting an element of <m>G</m> that's not appeared in <m>H</m> or any of the ranges of functions from previous steps.   This process has to end in a finite number of steps and produces a partition of <m>G</m> into subsets all of the same cardinality as <m>H</m>.</p></solution>
</exercise>
</exercisegroup></exercises>
</section>
<section xml:id="handouts-109"><title>Some Theorems</title>
<p>Two of the theorems in Section 10.3 follow. In doing the exercises, you don't need to prove these theorems or the others in the section.</p>

<theorem xml:id="theorem-11-3-cancellation"><title>Cancellation Laws</title>
<idx>Cancellation in Groups </idx>
<statement><p>If <m>a</m>, <m>b</m>, and <m>c</m> are elements of group <m>G</m>, then
 <me>
 \begin{array}{lc}
 \textrm{left cancellation: }&amp; (a * b = a * c)  \Rightarrow b = c\\
 \textrm{right cancellation: }&amp;  (b * a = c * a) \Rightarrow b = c\\
 \end{array}
 </me>
</p></statement>
</theorem>

<theorem xml:id="theorem-11-3-finite"><title>last theorem in Section 11.3</title>
<statement><p> If <m>G</m> is a finite group,  <m>\left| G\right| = n</m>, and <m>a</m> is an element of <m>G</m>, then there exists a positive integer <m>m</m> such
that <m>a^m= e</m> and <m>m\leq n</m>.</p></statement>
</theorem> 


</section>
</chapter>