<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<chapter xml:id="chapter_118" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Cosets</title>
<idx></idx>
<section xml:id="reading-118"><title>Reading Assignment</title>
<p>Read Section 15.2 of <em>Applied Discrete Structures</em>. If you get confused in this section, think about the partition of the integers into even integers and odd integers.  There is a consistency in doing arithmetic on the integers where, for example, any time you add an even integer and an odd integer, you get an odd integer.  So <m>\textrm{even} + \textrm{odd} = \textrm{even}</m>.  This is coset addition!  For any group, the only way something like this can work is when the partition is into cosets, which is why we start by defining this set of subsets of a group. </p>
<question><title>Response Question</title><statement><p>  How did Galois die, and why am I asking you this? </p></statement></question>
<p>Also, turn in solutions to these exercises: 
	<ol marker="1."><li>What does Lagrange's Theorem say about the possible subgroups of a group of order 12?</li>
		<li>Let <m>H</m> be the subgroup <m>\{0,25,50,75\}</m> of the additive group <m>\mathbb{Z}_{100}</m>. How many distinct left cosets are there of <m>H</m>?  What coset contains the number 42? List its elements.</li>
		</ol>  </p>
</section>
<section xml:id="questions-118"><title>In-Class Exercises</title>
<p>
<ol marker="1.">
<li><p>List the distinct left cosets of the cyclic subgroup of <m>U_{13}</m> generated by 3. To what other group is the factor group of these cosets isomorphic?</p></li>
<li><p>For each group and subgroup, to what simpler group is  <m>G/H</m> isomorphic?  Draw a picture of the groups and their cosets.
		<ol marker="(a)">
		<li><p>  <m>G= \mathbb{R}^2</m>  and  <m>H = \{(a,a) \mid a\in\mathbb{R}\}</m></p></li>
		<li><p>  <m>G = \mathbb{Z}_2^3</m>  and  <m>H = \langle 111 \rangle</m>.  In this group, write triples as bit strings of length 3. </p></li>
		</ol>
	</p></li>
<li><p>Consider the subgroup <m>C = \{00000, 01101, 11110, 10011\}</m> of the group <m>S=\mathbb{Z}_2^5</m>. Suppose your answer to a multiple choice question with four possible responses is stored in five bits of computer memory using one of the four elements of  <m>C</m>.  Now suppose the computer is hacked but we know that no more than one of the five bits in your response has been changed.  Can your response be recovered?</p></li>
</ol>
</p>
</section>
<!-- 
<section xml:id="handouts-118"><title>Handouts</title>
<p>None</p>
</section>
 -->
</chapter>	