<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<chapter xml:id="chapter_5" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Partitions and Combinations</title>
<idx></idx>
<section xml:id="reading-5"><title>Reading</title>
<p>Read Sections 2.3 and 2.4 of Applied Discrete Structures.</p>
<p>Response question: In mathematics, the word partition is used in two contexts. One is for partitions of sets, as described in Section 2.3. The other is for partitions of a positive integer.  An example of a partition of <m>5</m> is <m>3+1+1</m>, a sum of positive integers equal to <m>5</m>. It is customary to write the terms of the sum in non-increasing order since <m>1+3+1</m> is considered the same partition of <m>5</m>. The other partitions of 5 are <m>5</m>, <m>4+1</m>, <m>3+2</m>, <m>2+2+1</m>, <m>2+1+1+1</m>, and <m>1+1+1+1+1</m>. How might a listing of all partitions of an integer like <m>5</m> help in listing all partitions of a set with that many elements?</p>

<p>Exercises to do and turn in:
   <ol><li>2.3 #2</li>
   <li>2.4  #4</li>
   </ol>
</p>
</section>
<section xml:id="questions-5"><title>In-Class Questions</title>
<p>
<ol label="1.">
<li><p>Section 2.3 #6</p></li>
<li><p>How many different partitions are there of the set <m>\{1,2,3,4,5\}</m></p></li>
<li><p>How many ways can you arrange the letters in the word BOOKKEEPER?</p></li>
<li><p>Section 2.4 #12</p></li>
<li><p>Section 2.4 #5</p></li>
<li><p>Section 2.4 #6</p></li>
<li><p>Consider the set of lattice paths from <m>(0,0)</m> to <m>(8,8)</m>.  You should know one quick formula for the cardinality of that set.  However, counting a different way can lead to an interesting  identity involving binomial coefficients.  Notice that any path goes through exactly one of the points <m>(0,8), (1,7), (2,6), \dots , (8,0)</m>.  Count the number of lattice paths that go through each of those 9 points - leave the expression in terms of binomial coefficients.  Even more interesting is what you get if  generalize to a destination of <m>(n,n)</m>, <m>n \geq 1</m>. </p></li>
</ol>
</p>
</section>
<section xml:id="handouts-5"><title>Some Lattices</title>
<p>Here are a couple of lattices for you to doodle with.</p>
		<figure><caption/>
		 <image width="75%" source="images/graphpaper8.png">
			  <description>An 8 by 8 lattice.</description>
		 </image>
		 </figure>
		<figure><caption/>
		 <image width="75%" source="images/graphpaper8.png">
			  <description>Another 8 by 8 lattice.</description>
		 </image>
		 </figure>
			 
</section>
</chapter>