<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<chapter xml:id="chapter_10" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Quantifiers and Proof Review</title>
<idx></idx>
<section xml:id="reading-10"><title>Reading Assignment</title>
<p>Read Sections 3.8 and 3.9 of <em>Applied Discrete Structures</em>.  Quantifiers are used to say something about the truth sets of propositions.  You will read about two basic ones (Universal and Existential).  Individually, they are fairly simple.  Where things can be tricky is when when you have more than one variable and you mix the two types of quantifiers, or you negate a quantified expression.  Pay close attention to these situations. </p>
<question><title>Response Question</title><statement><p>  In reviewing a certain local coffee roaster, a writer stated  "...but all of its coffee is not fair trade." The writer was rebutting a claim by the roaster that "All of our coffee is fair trade."  Explain why the reviewer's statement was incorrect. </p></statement></question>
<p>Also, turn in solutions to these exercises: </p>
	<exercises><exercisegroup>
<exercise><statement> <p>Let <m>M(x)</m> be <q><m>x</m> is a mammal,</q> let <m>A(x)</m> be <q><m>x</m> is an animal,</q> and let <m>W(x)</m> be <q><m>x</m> is warm-blooded.</q></p>
<p><ol marker="(a)">
<li><p>Translate into a formula: Every mammal is warm-blooded.</p></li>
<li><p>Translate into English: <m>(\exists x)(A(x) \land  (\neg M(x)))</m>.</p></li>
</ol>
</p></statement></exercise>
		
<exercise><statement><p>Write out a complete proof that if <m>n</m> is an integer, <m>n^2</m> is even if and only if <m>n</m> is even.
</p></statement></exercise>
		</exercisegroup></exercises>  
</section>
<section xml:id="questions-10"><title>In-Class Exercises</title>
<p></p>
<exercises><exercisegroup>

<exercise><statement><p>
        Translate the following statement over the positive integers into symbols. Use <m>E(x)</m> for <q><m>x</m> is even</q> and <m>O(x)</m> for <q><m>x</m> is odd</q> in the first three parts.
       <ol marker="(a)">
          <li><p>No number is both even and odd. </p></li>
          <li><p>One more than any even number is an odd number.</p></li>
          <li><p>There is prime number that is even. </p></li>
          <li><p>Between any two numbers there is a third number.</p></li>
          <li><p>There is no number between a number and one more than that number.
            </p></li>
        </ol>
      </p></statement></exercise>

<exercise><statement><p>Use quantifiers to state that for every positive integer, there is a larger positive integer.</p></statement></exercise>

<exercise><statement><p>One of the following is true and the other is false.  Identify the true one says and explain why the other one is false.
		<md>
		<mrow>(\exists  b)_{\mathbb{Z}} ((\forall a)_{\mathbb{Z}}(a + b = 0))</mrow>
		<mrow>(\forall  a)_{\mathbb{Z}} ((\exists b)_{\mathbb{Z}}(a + b = 0))</mrow>
		</md>
</p></statement></exercise>

<exercise><statement><p>Prove that the sum of of an odd integer and and even integer is odd.</p></statement></exercise>

<exercise><statement><p>Prove that if you divide 4 into a perfect square, <m>1, 4, 9, 16, \dots</m>, the remainder will be either 0 or 1.</p></statement></exercise>

<exercise><statement><p>Prove that the cube root of <m>2</m> is an irrational number.</p></statement></exercise>
</exercisegroup></exercises>

</section>
</chapter>	