<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<chapter xml:id="chapter_102" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Graphs</title>
<idx>Graphs</idx>
<section xml:id="reading-102"><title>Reading Assignment</title>
<p>Read Section 9.1 of <em>Applied Discrete Structures</em>. This section introduces some basic terminology and properties of graphs.</p>
<question><title>Response Question</title><statement><p>The original version of the computer language BASIC on Apple II computers used 16 bits for an integer, one of which was used to specify the sign of the integer.  What would have been the maximum size of an integer in that language?</p>	</statement></question>
<p>Also, turn in solutions to these exercises: 
	<ul>
		<li><p>Why is the sum of the degrees of the vertices of any undirected graph always even?</p></li>
		<li><p>Demonstrate that <m>(4,3,2,2,1)</m> is a graphic sequence.</p></li>		
	</ul>  </p>
</section>
<section xml:id="questions-102"><title>In-Class Exercises</title>
<p>
<ol marker="1.">
<li><p>Prove that any graph with at least two vertices must have two vertices of the same degree.</p></li>
<li><p>Starting at vertex <m>s</m>, any finite path in <xref ref="fig-directed-graph-ex1" text="type-global"/> produces a string of bits that are recorded according to the labels on each edge.  For example, the path <m>s,a,b,a,b,b,a</m> will produce the string 101001.</p>				<figure xml:id="fig-directed-graph-ex1">
					<caption>A model for bit strings with no consecutive 1's</caption>
					<image  width="70%" source="images/fig-directed-graph-ex1.png">
					<description>A directed graph with three vertices, a start vertex and vertices labeled "a" and "b." For each vertex there are either one or two edges. Edges labeled 1 points to the "a" vertex, representing a state in which only a 0 can be the next bit.  From "a" only a "0 edge" is present, pointing to "b".  From other vertices a 0 edge points to "b." </description>
					</image>
					</figure>
<p>This graph produces bit strings that contain no consecutive 1's.   Draw a graph similar to it that produces bit strings containing no more than two consecutive 1's.</p></li>
<li><p>Find two isomorphisms between the following graphs.</p>						
				<figure xml:id="fig-graphpair">
					<caption>Two Isomorphic Graphs</caption>
					<image  width="70%" source="images/fig-graphpair.png">
					<description>Two isomorphic  undirected graphs with six vertices. The first has edge set {{1,6},{2,3},{2,5},{2,6},{3,6},{4,5},{4,6},{5,6}}, while the second has edge set  {{e,f},{a,b},{a,d},{a,f},{b,f},{c,d},{c,f},{d,f}} </description>
					</image>
					</figure>
</li>
<li><p>
<ol marker="(a)">
<li><p> Determine whether the following sequences are graphic. Explain your logic if the answer is <q>no</q> and draw a graph with the sequence as its degree sequence if it is <q>yes.</q>
<ol marker="i">
<li><p>  <m>(5,1,1,1,1,1)</m></p></li>
<li><p> <m>(3,3,3,3)</m></p></li>
<li><p> <m>(3,3,3,3,3)</m></p></li>
<li><p> <m>(4,3,2,1,0)</m></p></li>
<li><p> <m>(2,2,2,1,1)</m></p></li>
<li><p> <m>(3,2,2,2,1)</m></p></li>
</ol></p></li>
<li><p>Based on observations you might have made in from the examples above, describe as many characteristics as you can about graphic sequences.</p></li>
</ol>


</p></li>
</ol>
</p>
</section>
<!-- 
<section xml:id="handouts-102"><title>Handouts</title>
<p>None</p>
</section>
 -->
</chapter>	