<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<chapter xml:id="chapter_111" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Subsystems</title>
<idx>Subsystem</idx><idx>Subgroup</idx><idx>Cyclic Subgroup</idx>
<section xml:id="reading-111"><title>Reading Assignment</title>
<p>Read Section 11.5 of <em>Applied Discrete Structures</em>. The main idea is that there are certain subsets of groups that qualify as groups in their own right.  This is an instance of a more general situation in mathematics where a structure can contain smaller structures.  The idea of a subset is the most simple case of this, but we have also seen subgraphs in the study of graphs and trees.  Finding all subgroups of a group isn't always easy, but describing and finding the cyclic subgroups of a group is not too difficult.  Pay close attention how this is done!</p>
<question><title>Response Question</title><statement><p>Let <m>m \mathbb{Z} = \{m \cdot k \mid k \in \mathbb{Z}\}</m>. Chris says that <m>7 \mathbb{Z}</m> is a subgroup of <m>14 \mathbb{Z}</m> because <m>7 \leq 14</m>.   How would you respond to Chris?</p></statement></question>
<p>Also, turn in solutions to these exercises:</p> 
<exercises><exercisegroup>
		<exercise><statement><p>True or false?:  The set of all bit strings that begin with a 1 form a submonoid of the monoid of all bit strings with concatination.</p></statement>
		<solution><p>The statement is false because the empty string doesn't start with a 1 and so the identity element is not in the given set. Explain your answer.</p></solution></exercise>
		<exercise><statement><p>True or false?: <m>\{0,25,50,75\}</m> is a subgroup of the additive group <m>\mathbb{Z}_{100}</m>. Explain your answer.</p></statement><solution><p></p></solution></exercise>
		</exercisegroup></exercises>
</section>
<section xml:id="questions-111"><title>In-Class Exercises</title>
<p></p> 
<exercises><exercisegroup>
		<exercise><statement><p>Determine the cyclic subgroup generated by 4 in the group <m>\mathbb{Z}_{11}</m></p></statement><solution><p></p></solution></exercise>
		<exercise><statement><p>Determine the cyclic subgroup generated by 4 in the group <m>\mathbb{U}_{11}</m></p></statement><solution><p></p></solution></exercise>
		<exercise><statement><p>In this exercise, we will consider the orders of the additive groups of integers modulo <m>n</m> for three different values of <m>n</m>, and then speculate on some general results.
		<ol marker="(a)">
		<li><p>Determine the orders of different elements of the group <m>\mathbb{Z}_{5}</m>.</p></li>
		<li><p>Determine the orders of different elements of the group <m>\mathbb{Z}_{15}</m>.</p></li>
		<li><p>Determine the orders of different elements of the group <m>\mathbb{Z}_{16}</m>.</p></li>
		<li><p>Comparing the results you got above, hypothesize on what you would expect for different moduli</p></li>
		</ol></p></statement>
		<solution><p></p></solution></exercise>
		
		<exercise><statement><p>Assume that <m>[G;*]</m> is a group and <m>H</m> is a nonempty subset of <m>G</m>. Suppose that we are told that for <m>a, b \in H</m>, we are guaranteed that <m>a^{-1}*b \in H</m>.  Prove that <m>H</m> is a subgroup of <m>G</m>.</p></statement><hint><p>Prove the identity, inverses and closure properties of a subgroup, in that order.</p></hint><solution><p></p></solution></exercise>
		</exercisegroup></exercises>
</section>
<section xml:id="handouts-111"><title>Handouts</title>
<p>Here is a reminder of the definition of the associative property.</p>
<definition xml:id="def-associative-property"><title>Associative Property</title><idx>Associative Property</idx><statement><p>Let <m>*</m> be a binary operation on a set <m>S</m>. We say that <m>*</m> is  <term>associative</term>  if and only if <m>(a * b) * c = a * (b * c)</m> for all <m>a, b, c \in  S</m>.</p></statement></definition>
</section>
</chapter>	