<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<chapter xml:id="chapter_105" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Trees and Spanning Trees  </title>
<idx></idx>
<section xml:id="reading-105"><title>Reading Assignment</title>
<p>Read Sections 10.1 and 10.2 of <em>Applied Discrete Structures</em>. In these sections we introduce trees, which are connected graphs without cycles.  We also examine spanning trees of connected graphs, which are the smallest subgraphs which maintain connectedness in a graph.</p>
<question><title>Response Question</title><statement><p>In general, a family tree isn't really a tree in the sense of graph theory. Explain why.  You can assume links in the family tree are undirected.</p></statement></question>
<p>Also, turn in solutions to these exercises:</p>
<exercises><exercisegroup>
		<exercise><statement><p>Given a tree with <m>n</m> vertices, <m>n \geq 2</m>, how many leaves (vertices of degree 1) could it have?</p></statement><solution><p></p></solution></exercise>
		<exercise><statement><p>What can you say about the sum of the entries in the degree sequence of a tree?</p></statement><solution><p></p></solution></exercise>
		</exercisegroup></exercises>
</section>
<section xml:id="questions-105"><title>In-Class Exercises</title>
<p></p>
<exercises><exercisegroup>
		<exercise><statement><p>Use the planarity of trees together with <xref ref="theorem-euler-formula-statement" text="title"/> to derive the relationship between the number of vertices and number of edges in a tree.</p>
		</statement><solution><p></p></solution></exercise>

		<exercise><statement><p>Prove that every tree is bipartite, i. e., has a 2-coloring.</p>
		</statement><solution><p></p></solution></exercise>

			<exercise><statement><p>Prove that every connected graph which is not itself a tree must have at last three different spanning trees.</p>
		</statement><solution><p></p></solution></exercise>

		<exercise><statement><p>Use Prim's algorithm starting at vertex 1 to find a minimal spanning tree for the following graph.</p>
		<figure xml:id="fig-prim-1"><caption/>
		 <image width="65%" source="images/fig-prim-1.png">
			  <description>A weighted undirected graph on 10 vertices. The edges are are given by the list of triples [[1,2,8],[1,5,6],[1,9,7],[1,10,10],[3,5,11],[3,7,9],[4,9,13],[5,8,12],[6,7,5],[6,10,13]], where the first two entries are the vertices of the edge and the last entry is its weight.</description>
		 </image>
		 </figure>
		</statement><solution><p>The edges that are added, in order are {1,5}, {1,9}, {1,2},{9,7}, {7,6},{7,3},{1,10},{5,8},{9,4}.  This assumes that if there is a tie in possibly adding an edge, the smallest vertex number is added, which is the case when {1,2} is added.</p></solution></exercise>
 <exercise>
    <statement>
      <p>
        For each degree sequence below, decide whether it must always, must never, or could possibly be a degree sequence for a tree.  If it is always a tree, is the tree unique?  Justify your answers. (Adapted from <xref ref="biblio-levin-2020"/>.)
        <ol>
          <li>
            <p>
              <m>(3, 3, 2, 2, 2)</m>
            </p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>
              <m>(3, 2, 2, 1, 1, 1)</m>
            </p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>
              <m>(3, 3, 3, 1, 1, 1)</m>
            </p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>
              <m>(4, 4, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1)</m>
            </p>
          </li>
        </ol>
      </p>
    </statement>
  </exercise>		</exercisegroup></exercises>
</section>
<section xml:id="handouts-105"><title>Euler's Formula</title>

<theorem xml:id="theorem-euler-formula-statement"><title>Euler's Formula</title><idx>Euler's Formula</idx>
<statement>
<p>If <m>G = (V, E)</m> is a connected planar graph with <m>r</m> regions, <m>v</m> vertices, and <m>e</m> edges, then
<me>v + r - e = 2</me></p></statement>
</theorem></section>
</chapter>
