<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<chapter xml:id="chapter_114" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Posets and Lattices</title>
<idx>Poset</idx><idx>Lattice</idx>
<section xml:id="reading-114"><title>Reading Assignment</title>
<p>Read Sections 13.1 and 13.2 of <em>Applied Discrete Structures</em>. Partial orderings were introduced in Chapter 6 and you might want to review the definition before you start on Chapter 13. You might recall that partial orderings tend to compare certain pairs of elements in a poset according to some size, where size might not always mean size in the conventional sense.  In any case, if we take two elements from a poset, an upper bound is something in the poset that is comparably larger than them both.  A lower bound is defined similarly. In some cases, we can define binary operations (<q>join</q> and <q>meet</q>) based on this idea.  When we can, we get an algebraic structure called a <em>lattice</em>. </p>
<question><title>Response Question</title><statement><p>   Google “total ordering” and find out if a total ordering is a “partial ordering.” </p></statement></question>
<p>Also, turn in solutions to these exercises:</p>
<exercises>
	<exercise>
<statement>
 <p> For the poset <m>(\mathbb{N},\leq )</m>, what are the greatest lower bound and least upper bound of two elements <m>a</m> and <m>b</m>? Are there least and/or greatest elements?</p></statement></exercise>
	<exercise>
<statement><p>Let <m>L</m> be the set of all propositions generated by <m>p</m> and <m>q</m>.  What are the meet and join operations in this lattice under implication?   What are the maximum and minimum elements?</p></statement></exercise>
	</exercises>
</section>
<section xml:id="questions-114"><title>In-Class Exercises</title>
<p> </p>
<exercises>
<exercise><statement><p>Consider the poset <m>(D_{50},\mid)</m>, where <m>D_{50} = \{1,2,5,10,25,50\}</m>.
<ol marker="(a)">
<li><p>   Find all lower bounds of 10 and 25.</p></li>
<li><p>   Find the greatest lower bound  of 10 and 25.</p></li>
<li><p>   Find all upper bounds of 10 and 25.</p></li>
<li><p>   Determine the least upper bound  of 10 and 25.</p></li>
<li><p>   Draw the Hasse diagram for <m>D_{50}</m> with respect to <m>\mid</m>.</p></li>
</ol></p></statement></exercise>
<exercise>
	<statement><p>Demonstrate that the pentagon lattice is nondistributive.</p></statement>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<statement><p> We naturally order the numbers in <m>A_m = \{1, 2, . . . , m\}</m> with <q>less than or equal to,</q> which is a partial ordering. We define an ordering, <m>\preceq</m>  on the elements of <m>A_m \times  A_n</m> by
 <me>(a, b) \preceq  (a', b') \Leftrightarrow a \leq  a' \textrm{ and } b \leq  b'</me>
<ol marker="(a)">
<li><p> Prove that <m>\preceq</m> is a partial ordering on <m>A_m \times  A_n</m>.</p></li>
<li><p> Draw the ordering diagrams for <m>\preceq</m> on <m>A_2 \times  A_2</m>, <m>A_2\times  A_3</m>, and <m>A_3 \times  A_3</m>.</p></li>
<li><p>In general, how does one determine the least upper bound  and greatest lower bound of two elements of <m>A_m \times  A_n</m>, <m>(a, b)</m> and <m>(a',b')</m>?</p></li>
<li><p>Are there least and/or greatest elements in <m>A_m \times  A_n</m>?</p></li>
</ol></p></statement></exercise>
<exercise>	
<statement><p>The last question you answered with the readings for this class is actually not very precise.  For example,  is it true that  <m>p \Rightarrow p\land(p \lor q)</m> or  <m>p\land(p \lor q) \Rightarrow p</m>, or are both true?  If both are true, what does that say about the relation <m>\Rightarrow</m>?   This would present a problem, but it can be fixed by considering the elements of our poset to be equivalence classes.  What would be the equivalence classes?</p>
</statement></exercise>
</exercises>
</section>
<section xml:id="handouts-114"><title>Nondistributive lattices</title>
<idx>Non-distributive lattices</idx>
<p>Here are the fundamental nondistributive lattices.</p>
 <figure xml:id="fig-nondistributive-lattices">
                <caption>Nondistributive lattices, the pentagon and diamond lattices
                </caption>
                <image width="50%" source="images/fig-nondistributive-lattices.png">
                    <description>Nondistributive Lattices</description>
                </image>
            </figure>
</section>
</chapter>