<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<chapter xml:id="chapter_120" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Permutation Groups, Part 2</title>
<idx></idx>
<section xml:id="reading-120"><title>Reading Assignment</title>
<p>Read the rest of  Section 15.3 of <em>Applied Discrete Structures</em>. The family <m>S_n</m> of symmetric groups is extremely important in group theory, particularly when it comes to doing computations.   There is a theorem called Cayley's Theorem that essentially says that <em>every</em> group is  subgroup of some symmetric group.  This means that if you intend to do group computations, it's natural to implement the work in terms of permutations. </p>
<question><title>Response Question</title><statement><p>How is Rubik's cube related to permutation groups? </p></statement></question>
<p>Also, turn in solutions to these exercises: 
	<ul><li>Based on <em>Lagrange's Theorem</em>, what are the possible orders of subgroups of the group <m>S_4</m>?</li>
		<li> The <em>shape</em> of a permutation, <m>\sigma</m> in <m>S_n</m> is the sequence of lengths of the cycles in the representaion of <m>\sigma</m> as a product of disjoint cycles. The lengths are written in descending order.  For example, if <m>\sigma = (1,3,4)(8,11)(2,5,6,7)(9,10)(12) \in S_{12}</m>, then its shape is  4,3,2,2,1.  List all possible shapes of elements in <m>S_4</m>.</li>
		</ul>  </p>
</section>
<section xml:id="questions-120"><title>In-Class Exercises</title>
<p>
<ol marker="1.">
<li><p>Prove that <m>H =\{\sigma \in S_5 \mid \sigma(5)=5 \}</m> is a subgroup of <m>S_5</m>.  How many elements does <m>H</m> have?</p></li>
<li><p>Given a graph with vertex set <m>\{1, 2, 3, 4, 5\}</m>, the group of automorphisms of that graph will be a subgroup of the group  <m>S_4</m>. For each of the following subgroups of <m>S_5</m>, draw a graph (directed or undirected) that has that subgroup as its automorphism group.
		<ol marker="(a)">
			<li><p><m>\{i\}</m></p></li>
			<li><p>The cyclic subgroup generated by <m>(1,2)</m></p></li>
			<li><p>The cyclic subgroup generated by <m>(1,2,3,4,5)</m></p></li>
			<li><p><m>\{\sigma \in S_5 \mid \sigma(5)=5  \}</m></p></li>
		</ol>
</p></li>
<li><p>There are subgroups of <m>S_n</m> that are not the automorphism group of of any graph with <m>n</m> vertices.  Illustrate this fact by showing that it is true for <m>S_4</m>.  However, for any such subgroup, <m>H</m>, there are graphs with a larger number of vertices that have automorphism groups that are isomorphic to <m>H</m>. Illustrate this fact with the subgroup you identified in <m>S_4</m>.   </p></li>
</ol>
</p>
</section>
<!-- 
<section xml:id="handouts-120"><title>Handouts</title>
<p>None</p>
</section>
 -->
</chapter>	