<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<chapter xml:id="chapter_122" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Algebraic Coding, Part 2</title>
<idx></idx>
<section xml:id="reading-122"><title>Reading Assignment</title>
<p>Read the rest of  Section 15.5 of <em>Applied Discrete Structures</em>.  We consider how to correct transmission errors by using redundant information in a coded message.  This avoids having to ask for a message to be resent from the sender.</p>
<question><title>Response Question</title><statement><p>Who was Claude Shannon and what is his connection with coding theory?  </p></statement></question>
<p>Also, turn in solutions to these exercises: 
	
<ol marker="1.">
		<li><p>What is the minimum Hamming distance between code words in the set <m>\{11100,00111,10001,01010\}</m>?  	
				Without doing any calculation, how can you tell 
					<me>\{11100,00111,10001,01010\}</me> 
				cannot be the code words of a linear code?</p></li>
		<li><p>I'm a liar, but not a big one.  In my responses to your yes/no questions, I promise not to lie more 
			than one time. My favorite number is 0, 1, 2, or 3.  How many yes/no questions do you need to ask in 
			order to figure it out? You need to submit all of your questions to me without waiting for my answers.
			 (thanks to Daniel Glasscock for this problem)</p></li>
</ol>  
</p>
</section>
<section xml:id="questions-122"><title>In-Class Exercises</title>
<p>
<ol marker="1.">
<li><p>Suppose a two bit message is encoded into a five bit message using the function <m>e(b_{1}b_{2})=b_{1}b_{1}(b_{1}+_2 b_{2})b_{2}b_{2}</m>.  Determine a matrix <m>P</m> such that if a two bit message, <m>b = b_{1}b_{2}</m>, is encoded and <m>e(b)</m> transmitted, then any single bit error in the received string <m>c=c_{1}c_{2}c_{3}c_{4}c_{5}</m> can be identified by whether <m>c P</m> is the zero vector or not.</p></li>

<li><p>Consider the  linear code defined by the generator matrix
<me>G=\left(
\begin{array}{cccc}
 1 &amp; 0 &amp; 1 &amp; 0 \\
 0 &amp; 1 &amp; 1 &amp; 1 \\
\end{array}
\right)</me></p>
<p>
<ol marker="(a)">
<li><p>  What size blocks does this code encode and what is the length of the code words?</p></li>
<li><p>  What are the code words for this code?</p></li>
<li><p>  With this code, can you detect single bit errors?  Can you correct all, some, or no single bit errors?</p></li>
</ol>  
</p></li>
<li><idx>Rectangular Code</idx><p>To build a <term>rectangular code</term>, you partition your message into blocks of length <m>m</m> and then factor <m>m</m> into <m>k_1\cdot k_2</m>  and arrange the bits in a  <m>k_1 \times k_2</m> rectangular array as in the figure below.  Then you add parity bits along the right side and bottom of the rows and columns.   The code word is then read row by row.    

  <me>\begin{array}{cccccc}
 \blacksquare  &amp; \blacksquare  &amp; \blacksquare  &amp; \cdots  &amp; \blacksquare  &amp; \square  \\
 \blacksquare  &amp; \blacksquare  &amp; \blacksquare  &amp; \cdots  &amp; \blacksquare  &amp; \square  \\
 \vdots  &amp; \vdots  &amp; \vdots  &amp;   &amp; \vdots  &amp; \vdots  \\
 \blacksquare  &amp; \blacksquare  &amp; \blacksquare  &amp; \cdots  &amp; \blacksquare  &amp; \square  \\
 \square  &amp; \square  &amp; \square  &amp; \cdots  &amp; \square  &amp;   \\
\end{array}  \quad \begin{array}{c}
 \textrm{      }\blacksquare  = \textrm{ message} \textrm{ bit} \\
 \square  =\textrm{ parity} \textrm{ bit} \\
\end{array}</me>
</p>
<p>For example, if <m>m</m> is 4, then our only choice is a 2 by 2 array.  The message 1101 would be encoded as 
<me>\begin{array}{cc|c}
1 &amp; 1 &amp; 0\\
0 &amp; 1 &amp; 1\\
\hline
1 &amp; 0 &amp;\\
\end{array}</me>
and the code word is the string 11001110.</p>
<p>
<ol marker="(a)">
<li><p>Suppose that you were sent four bit messages using this code and you received the following strings.  What were the messages, assuming no more than one error in the transmission of coded data?
			<ol marker="(i)" cols="3">
			<li><p>11011000</p></li>
			<li><p>01110010</p></li>
			<li><p>10001111</p></li>
			</ol></p></li>
<li><p>If you encoded <m>n^2</m> bits in this manner, what would be the rate of the code?</p></li>
<li><p>Rectangular codes are linear codes.  For the 3 by 2 rectangular code, what are the generator and parity check matrices?</p></li>
</ol>
</p></li>
		<li><p>A code with minimum distance <m>d</m> is called <em>perfect</em> if every string of bits is within Hamming distance <m>r=\frac{d-1}{2}</m> of some codeword. For such a code, the spheres of radius <m>r</m> around the codewords partition the set of all strings.  This is analogous to packing objects into a box with no wasted space.  Using just the number of bit strings of length <m>n</m> and the number of strings in a sphere of radius <m>1</m>, for what values of <m>n</m> is it possible to find a perfect code of distance <m>3</m>?  You don't have to actually find the codes.</p></li>

</ol>
</p>
</section>
<!-- 
<section xml:id="handouts-122"><title>Handouts</title>
<p>None</p>
</section>
 -->
</chapter>	