<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<chapter xml:id="chapter_104a" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Planarity and Graph Coloring</title>
<idx>Planarity</idx><idx>Graph Coloring</idx><idx>Chromatic Polynomial</idx>
<section xml:id="reading-104a"><title>Reading Assignment</title>
<p>Read Section 9.6 of <em>Applied Discrete Structures</em>. There are two main topics of this section. The first is planarity of graphs, whether a graph can be drawn on paper without having any edges crossing one another.  The second is coloring, the vertices of a graph are assigned colors with the rule that two vertices that are connected by an edge must have different colors.  The two topics are unified by the Four Color Theorem.</p>
<question><title>Response Question</title><idx>F치ry, Istv치n</idx><statement><p>Who was Istv치n F치ry and what did he prove about planar graphs?</p></statement></question>
<p>Also, turn in solutions to these exercises:</p> 
<exercises><exercisegroup>
		<exercise><statement><p>Although a <m>K_{3,3}</m> it is not planar, it can be embedded on a torus without any edge crossings.  This is demonstrated in the video <url ref="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=k2O0Av_8_fo">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=k2O0Av_8_fo</url>.  Watch the video and then dermine whether you can embed a <m>K_5</m> on a torus without any edge crossings.</p></statement><solution><p>_</p></solution></exercise>
		<exercise><statement><p>Find a coloring of the following graph with as few colors as possible.  Use the letters <m>A,B,C,  \dots</m>> for colors and submit your answer in the form of a partition of <m>>\{1,2,\dots, 8\}</m>:
<me>\{\textrm{set of vertices with color }A, \textrm{set of vertices with color }B, \dots\}</me>> 

</p>
		<sidebyside>
		<figure xml:id="fig-colorme-1"><caption/>
		 <image width="65%" source="images/fig-colorme-1.png">
			  <description>An undirected graph on 8 vertices. The edges are are given by the set {(1,5), (1,6), (1,7), (1,8), (2,3), (2,6), (2,7), (3,4), (3,5), (3,8), (4,7), (6,7)}.</description>
		 </image>
		 </figure>
		 <p><me>\begin{array}{cccccccc}
 1 &amp; 2 &amp; 3 &amp; 4 &amp; 5 &amp; 6 &amp; 7 &amp; 8 \\
 \_\_ &amp; \_\_ &amp; \_\_ &amp; \_\_ &amp; \_\_ &amp;
   \_\_ &amp; \_\_ &amp; \_\_ \\
\end{array}</me></p>
		 </sidebyside></statement><solution><p></p></solution></exercise>
 		</exercisegroup></exercises>
</section>
<section xml:id="questions-104a"><title>In-Class Exercises</title>
<p></p> 
<exercises><exercisegroup>
			<exercise><statement><p>If a planar graph <m>G</m> with 12 vertices divides the plane into 21 regions, how many edges must <m>G</m> have?</p></statement><solution><p>Using Euler's formula, since <m>v+r-e=12+21-e=2</m>, <m>e=31</m> </p></solution></exercise>
	<exercise><statement><p>The graph <m>G</m> has vertices with degree sequence <m>(5, 3, 3, 2, 2, 1)</m>. How many edges does it have? If it is planar, into how many regions of the plane does it divide?  Does <m>G</m> have an Eulerian path?</p></statement>
		<answer><p>The degree sequence indicates that <m>v=6</m> and <m>e=8</m>. Since <m>v +r - e=6+r-8=2</m>, <m>r = 4</m>.</p></answer></exercise>
	<exercise><statement><p>Suppose an undirected planar graph <m>G</m> has the following properties:
	<ul><li><p>All vertices have degree three (this called a <term>cubic graph</term>)</p></li>
	<li><p>All faces of the graph's planar embedding are hexagons and pentagons; i. e,, they is made up of either five or six edges.</p></li></ul>
	What can be said about the numbers of hexagons and pentagons in the graph?</p></statement>
		<answer><p>There must be 12 pentagons. The number of hexagons cannot be determined.</p></answer></exercise>
		

		<exercise><statement><p>A teacher decides to have their students grade one another's quizzes.  The scheme that is devised is that when a bell is rung, each  student is to immediately pass their quiz to a classmate either to the front, back, right or left of themselves.  Suppose that class is arranged in rectanglar configuration of five rows of seven students each. Is is possible for each student to get exactly one quiz to grade?
	</p></statement><solution><p></p></solution></exercise>
		</statement><solution><p></p></solution></exercise>
		<exercise><idx>chromatic polynomial of a graph</idx><statement><p>The chromatic polynomial of a graph, <m>G</m> is a polynomial <m>g(x)</m> such that for each positive integer <m>n</m>, <m>g(n)</m> equals the number of different ways you can color <m>G</m> with <m>n</m> colors.  For example, the chromatic polynomial of a <m>K_3</m> is <m>x(x-1)(x-2)</m>.
		<ol label="(a)">
		<li><p>What is the chromatic polynomial of a <m>K_4</m>?</p></li>
		<li><p>What is the chromatic polynomial of a <m>C_4</m>, a cycle with four vertices?</p></li>
		<li><p>What is the chromatic polynomial of a <m>K_{3,3}</m>?</p></li>
		<li><p>How are the chromatic number and the chromatic polynomial of a graph related?</p></li>
		</ol></p></statement><solution><p></p></solution></exercise>
		
		</exercisegroup></exercises>
</section>
<!-- 
<section xml:id="handouts-104a"><title>Handouts</title>
<p>None</p>
</section>
 -->
</chapter>	