<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!-- This file is part of the book                 -->
<!--                                               -->
<!--   Active Applied Discrete Structures   -->
<!--                                               -->
<!-- Ken Levasseur    -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.  -->

<frontmatter xml:id="index-active-ads" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

	<titlepage>

		<author>
			<personname>Ken Levasseur</personname>
			<department>Department of Mathematical Sciences</department>
			<institution>University of Massachusetts Lowell</institution>
			<email>kenneth_levasseur@uml.edu</email>
		</author>

 
        <date><today /></date>


	</titlepage>

	<colophon>
		<edition> version 1.0</edition>
		<website>
			<name>discretemath.org</name>
			<address>http://discretemath.org</address>
    	</website>


		<copyright>
			<year>2021</year>
			<holder>Ken Levasseur</holder>
			<minilicense>Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 United States License. 2011-2017</minilicense>
<!-- 
			<creativecommons BY="yes" NC="yes" SA="yes" version="4.0"/>
 -->
			<shortlicense>Active Applied Discrete Structures by Kenneth Levasseur is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 United States License. You are free to Share: copy and redistribute the material in any medium or format; Adapt: remix, transform, and build upon the material. You may not use the material for commercial purposes.  The licensor cannot revoke these freedoms as long as you follow the license terms.
			</shortlicense>
		</copyright>
		
	</colophon>
<!-- 
<dedication>
<title>Dedication</title>
<p>To Karen</p>
</dedication>
 -->
	<!-- Accepted order: acknowledgements, forewords, prefaces -->
<!-- 
<xi:include href="./acknowledgement.xml" />
 -->
<preface xml:id="active-ads-preface"><title>Preface</title>
    <paragraphs>
        <title>Introduction</title>

        <p><em>Active Applied Discrete Structures</em> is designed for use in a flipped class using <em>Applied Discrete Structures</em>. Each chapter, designed for a 75 minute class period.  There are two parts that correspond with a two semester sequence, <em>Part 1 - Fundamentals</em>, and <em>Part 2 - Structures</em>. </p>
    </paragraphs>
	<paragraphs>
        <title>Usage</title>
		<p> The class format that is presumed is for the instructor to assign students to read materials that will be covered in class <m>n</m> in time for students to submit a short assignment by the beginning of class <m>n-1</m>. Then, at the time of class <m>n</m>, they work on more challenging problems in groups of 4-6 students.</p>
		<p>A tricky thing about this format is getting started. On class 1 of the first semester, no prior reading can be expected. The binary representation of positive integers is discussed. This is mostly done through group work. The assumption is that since most students in the class are computer science majors, they have some familiarity with the topic and can help  other students with the problems. Class 2 is also a bit of a rush. I ask students to do reading for that class and get responses back to me a couple of days before the second class. They are also asked to prepare for Class 3 and get responses to me by Class 2.   Fortunately, the material in Chapter 1 isn't too difficult.  The rest of the semester proceeds as described above. In the second semester, the first class is taken up by reviewing the most important concepts from the first semester through sequence of problems. Another quick turn-around in the reading for Class 2 is needed to get into the flow.  After that the second semester proceeds the same as the first.</p>
    </paragraphs>    
	<paragraphs>
        <title>Contents of the Chapters</title>
        <p>Each chapter has two or three sections.  Each chapter except the first has a reading section that contains instructions to student prior the class period. Generally, this is to read one or more sections of the text, respond to a <q>Response Question</q> and do a few basic problems associated with the reading.  The Response Questions tend to be more tangential to the content and often connect the mathematics to computer science.</p>
        <p>The second section is always a series of problems to be worked on during the class. For students' convenience, some chapters have a third section, usually containing a short excerpt from <em>Applied Discrete Structures</em>.</p>
    </paragraphs>

	<paragraphs>
        <title>The Problems</title>
        <p>The problems and ideas that make up this work come from several sources.  Many of the problems are taken directly from <em>Applied Discrete Structures</em>, mostly even numbered problems for which no solutions are published. In some cases, the problem are slightly altered.  I've also mined problems from other sources.  Some were clearly in the <q>public domain</q> in that they have appeared in several places over many years.  In those cases, I haven't identified the source.   There have been a few problems or ideas that seemed somewhat more novel, and I've noted their source. Books by Bogart (<xref ref="biblio-bogart-2017"/>) and Levin (<xref ref="biblio-levin-2020"/>) are among these sources.</p>
        <p>I've attempted to mix relatively easy problems with some more challenging ones for in-class work, while keeping the number of problems doable for most of the students.</p>    
    </paragraphs>
	<paragraphs>
	<title>Technology - Zoom and Piazza</title>
	<p>Halfway into testing Part 1 of this document, the Covid-19 pandemic forced my class online. The transition wasn't perfect, but by using Zoom and Piazza I managed to approximate the face-to-face experience to some degree.</p> 
	<p>After answering questions and a short introduction to the topic of the day, I distributed students into breakout rooms in Zoom.  The groups worked on the in-class problems and posted their solutions on Piazza.  Within a corresponding Piazza group, they would post the answer to on of the questions.  I could monitor each group's Piazza posts in real time, commenting on or endorsing the solutions.  If needed, I could also drop in on the group's breakout room to help out with any difficulties. Students were brought back to the main room for the final 15 minutes or so to review the solutions that were found by the groups.  Finally, I would pin correct solutions and make them available to the whole class as a record of the work done that day. This final step added value over what we would do in the face-to-face meetings. </p>
    </paragraphs>
    
    
	<paragraphs>
        <title>Status</title>
        <p>As of the spring of 2020, <em>Part 1 - Fundamentals</em>, contains 24 chapters class-tested in the first semester course at UMass Lowell. This covers the first eight chapters of <em>Applied Discrete Structures</em>. <em>Part 2 - Structures</em> will contain another 24 chapters for use in a second semester course. </p>
    </paragraphs>


<p>The main web page for Applied Discrete Structures is <url href="http://discretemath.org"/> </p>

			<attribution>
			<line>Ken Levasseur</line>
			<line>Lowell, MA</line>
			</attribution>
</preface>

<!-- 
<xi:include href="./introduction.xml" />
 -->

</frontmatter>